Hello Vegas.
Good morning.
It's nice to see your lovely faces so
early in Vegas. I hope you all weren't
out drinking too late last night.
This is a live taping, the first stop on
the Sub Club podcast world tour. So,
we'll be in London, New York, San
Francisco, Berlin later this year.
So, if you haven't heard of the Sub Club
podcast, I talk to industry experts like
Ramit every 2 weeks on the podcast. And
so, looking forward to this chat today.
Think there's a lot we can learn from
one of the leaders of some of the
biggest apps in the app stores. So,
yeah, my guest is Ramit. He's a lead PM
on monetization at Microsoft covering
Office 365 and Copilot. Yeah, and thanks
for joining me on the podcast today.
Thank you. Thank you so much. So, yeah,
I essentially am the growth lead for
Microsoft 365 apps for macOS and I
support growth for the mobile apps. So,
so essentially the core apps, Word,
Excel, PowerPoint. And also supporting
the Copilot app and the Microsoft 365
app as well. So, yeah.
All of them big apps. So, so yeah,
excited to talk about them and all views
are my own and do not represent
Microsoft's official stance. So, I'm
supposed to say that. So.
Okay.
Of course. One of the things when you
and I were first starting talking about
having this conversation today that
really struck me about our early
conversations is that it really sounds
like you and your team and even the kind
of app team inside Microsoft is like
started up inside a startup inside the
like biggest company in the world. I
always thought of Microsoft as
enterprise and people go to the web to
download Word and it's a native app on
Mac and I kind of always thought the
apps were almost an afterthought. But
the more we talked, it's like I mean,
Microsoft is very serious about building
fantastic apps and monetizing them on
the app stores.
Yes.
Yeah, so tell me a little bit about that
kind of approach and how you think about
growing an app business inside the
biggest company in the world.
Yeah. In the very, say, like 2013, 2014
era, these apps started as companion
apps to the desktop apps. So, there is
always this concept of desktop class
productivity, which is that you have a
screen, which is, say, an iPad or a
desktop, and that's where work gets
done. And then there's mobile
productivity, where you have light
edits. And then, over time, we started
to see that mobile being the primary
device a lot of customers. And this is
more true in Asia and other regions than
US, but mobile being the primary device
and not a shared device. So, people
have, say, in one family, they would be
like two like everybody will have a
phone and maybe they will have one
laptop. So, we started to see people
doing very long-form documents, like
sometimes up to 50 pages of documents
from their mobile phones. So, that's
when we started to get very serious
about this. And then the other trend
that we saw was that because App Store
has a very, very frictionless experience
for buying subscription, we started to
see that Microsoft 365 subscription,
especially in consumer, like our
personal and family subscriptions, and
now Copilot Pro, keeps seeing this trend
that people just want to make the
purchase from their phone. So, it's kind
of like how a lot of people buy from the
Amazon app rather than from the website
because it's just a more handy device.
There's when your credit card is
attached. And we see almost a 5x higher
trial to paid conversion rate on mobile
than on other direct channels sometimes
because of very obvious reasons like
this, credit card is already attached,
and there is a frictionless experience,
people trust providers like Apple,
Google, Amazon to essentially manage
their subscription. So, while we have a
very large direct business, we started
to see that App Store has this real
potential in terms of
very high trial to paid credit card
already attached, people having this as
their primary device. That's where
they're managing a lot of subscriptions
from.
Yeah.
So, those were some of the things and
then we started to get very serious and
App Store just gave us so much organic
traffic that sure we pay some percentage
to the App Stores, but anywhere you
acquire you have to pay some percentage.
So,
so so basically the organic traffic just
blew our mind and so we just invested
and and here we are.
Uh-huh.
It's so funny cuz Apple's so protective
of their percentage and I think people
discount just how much it being so
convenient is actually increasing
conversion rates and leading to new
subscribers who just wouldn't subscribe
on the web. So, you hadn't told me that
before sitting here on the stage that
you had seen a 5x increase in conversion
from trial. That that's incredible.
Yeah, yeah. In some platform I mean
obviously we we sell across multiple
platforms. I think only on consumer we
have like 10 different channels that we
are selling on. So, we have other
channels that also perform very well,
but App Store is one of the highest
performing in terms of trial to paid
conversion specifically.
Yeah, that's amazing. And how do you
view competing on the App Store though
as far as there are so many productivity
apps, you know, so many notes apps, so
many places that you can create
documents and everything like that. How
does a massive brand like Microsoft
approach competing in this marketplace
that is very different from the web?
Yeah, I mean it has been a bit of a
learning for sure, but one of the things
I will say so competing on App Store you
just have to operate like a startup
because if you see any other
distribution channel like a web or say
even retail partnerships, those kind of
things, we have some advantage there
that okay, we have an exclusive deal
with a retailer or we have a website
that has say millions of users that are
coming on on App Store it's very
democratic. App Store I like to think
about it like YouTube is, right? Like
Paramount Pictures and a YouTube
influencer, they're pretty much
competing for the same eyeballs. So, we
don't get a lot of advantage. Of course,
there is some brand value that we do
get. So, when we do our ASO, for
example, we have branded keywords, so
that's part of our strategy, and then
unbranded keywords. But, App Store is
unlike anything else in the sense that a
startup can start in Bangalore and start
taking the spot on some keyword and
start showing up above word, right? We
have to be like at our best game, and we
try to retain at least the top three
spots in most of the categories. And to
your other question, uh
being a massive brand, so think of this
as like startups are kind of like
department stores, and we are like the
Costco. So, we have all the scenarios.
We have I mean, if you look at our
Microsoft 365 apps specifically, like it
has Word, Excel, PowerPoint, notes, PDF,
signing, and there's
a scanner, and so there is so many
scenarios that are there. So, from a
value perspective, the value density is
very high for our app. So, for like
$9.99 for the family and $6.99 for
personal,
just the value that we can pack into one
app, and those prices are obviously US
prices. Some countries may be different,
but like just the value that we can pack
into one app, it can be up to
50 to 60% cheaper if you go and buy all
those scenarios individually versus you
buy like a M365 subscription. I know I'm
giving a very department store type of
methodology, but like you just see how
much value we can pack into one app, it
just blows, you know? I mean, if you try
to buy, say, a scanning subscription,
etc., etc., it will cost you a lot more
than buying one from Microsoft. And the
other thing that it also helps us is
that a lot of productivity scenarios are
very one-time use. So, like for example,
in 1 month, you will have one scanning
use case. In 1 month you will have one
say two document use case. But when you
combine everything together in one app,
then your retention is maintained
because, you know, you may have a
scanning use case today, but you may
have a document use case, then you may
have a So, overall on a suite level, we
see good retention because on a suite
level there is that retention which
which is maintained because of different
different use cases that people have a
use for.
Yeah. So, with the App Store being so
competitive, and I think this applies to
any app these days. It's it's so
commoditized. There's so many apps in
every category. Like I have a weather
app side project, and there's like 100
weather apps. And so, I'm constantly
thinking like how do I differentiate,
and how do I kind of stay ahead? As
Microsoft, you've got way more resources
to be able to think about those kind of
things, but how do you approach that
differentiation and adding enough value,
and kind of staying ahead of the curve?
There's no one good answer to something
like this, but in general, if I have to
talk about from a framework perspective,
if you're trying to maintain a
leadership position, and this applies to
like broader than App Store, then you
have to think about neutralization.
So, this is a framework that one of our
VPs used to talk about a lot. Like So,
you have to keep neutralizing any
competitor move, for example. Then you
have to keep differentiating. Then you
have to keep incubating, and you have to
keep maintaining on So, for example,
Apple releases dark mode, Apple release
Vision Pro. So, we always maintain a
leadership position in the sense that
our apps are already on Vision Pro day
one. We were day one dark mode. We were
day one on most of the new innovations
that come out. Like we are day one
there. So, as soon as something gets
launched in say WWDC, we are thinking,
"Okay, how does it apply?" And then,
depending on the stage of your app, like
if you're a mature app versus a startup,
you can like do different percentages.
like now say we do 30% incubation
because we are a more mature app. In In
the past we were more bothered with like
neutralization and differentiation, but
now we can just do a lot more incubation
because we have a base. And now we are
focusing on, okay, how can we bring AI?
How can we bring some of the more
advanced features that can pretty much
help people do complete document
creation on their mobile, like they
don't If you think about what AI can do
these days, like you don't need 10 tabs.
You can just pull all the information
like one place and create any artifact
like a document, video, etc. So, we are
very focused on that.
to talk more about AI, but before we
move on, I want to re-kind of state that
framework cuz I think a lot of apps can
use this. Like when you're competing,
thinking about neutralizing, so, you
know, when you see another app come out
with a very differentiated feature, you
might not like copy that. I mean,
especially you know, Microsoft, but like
as an app developer, finding a way to
neutralize that in that, like find your
own way to differentiate or or have some
form of functionality that handles
aspects of those use cases and then
differentiate, make sure that you create
new things that are differentiated,
maintain that leadership position, and
then incubate, like constantly be like
talking to users, like doing user
research, and trying new things.
Right.
And it's cool to hear that like, you
know, again, the biggest company in the
world thinks a lot like a startup and
thinks through these kind of frameworks
about neutralize, differentiate,
maintain, and incubate.
if you have an app on the App Store,
it's not like a bond you bought and
it'll keep paying dividends, you know.
Yeah. You have to keep working on it.
Like you have to keep at it and you have
to keep thinking about the next thing
and the next thing and the next thing
because it's a pretty competitive
marketplace. And the other thing that I
would also say is that
when you are thinking about these four
things,
I think it's very important to think
about them from the lens of jobs to be
done rather than like say this
competition brought something and then
we copy. We never copy. We genuinely
first see, okay, is this job even
important for the customer? So, I think
that's super important to have a very
clear even the largest apps. So, like
even if you take a an app such as Word,
there's a very defined set of jobs that
Word needs to do for a user. Like people
should be able to create a resume. They
should be able to create a note. They
should be able to write a book. Like I
can list out 10 things that Word should
be able to do or Excel. Like you know,
you used to be able to create a
spreadsheet, a budget, or invoice. So,
if the app is able to do all of those
things on any form factor, be it mobile,
iPad, or desktop, it's super important
that we focus on that aspect, that what
are we trying to do? And then there will
always be more So, we are a more
horizontal like from product standpoint.
We have a more horizontal solution.
There will always be more
vertical solutions. Like for example,
somebody would have a very, very tight
invoicing app which will have many, many
things like bank connections, etc. I
mean, Excel will not go that deep into
something like this. But then of course,
there could be add-ins that can support
something like that. So, there is that
horizontal versus vertical focus that
you have to think about. You can't go
too focused on one vertical if you're
trying to build a more horizontal
presence. So,
All right. So, now I want to do want to
get to AI. I think you know, so many
people I mean, it's such a buzzword.
There's so many AI apps doing really
well and so many people thinking like
what should our AI strategy be as an
app? And I think too many people are
throwing it in as a gimmick.
And not like deeply thinking through
like what is this new paradigm of AI
mean for our app and how can we
introduce it into the app in a way that
actually increases the value and like
people actually use it instead of just
being like some kind of gimmick you
throw in so that your title can say
whatever whatever AI. And then
Microsoft, it's like you get working on
Copilot and then being at Microsoft,
you've got like a front-row seat. But
not only that, but you work with a lot
of teams across the company, user
research, and other folks to really
understand how to take the best of AI
and implement them in a thoughtful way
that actually brings value. So, what's
that approach? Like how do you take this
new hot technology and actually make
something meaningful from it?
Yeah. So, so I mean, first of all, I am
myself kind of new to AI. And secondly,
whatever I will say will be irrelevant
in 1 month because it's going so fast
right now and things are changing so
fast. But I mean, let's just hone down
particularly into, say, generative AI.
Like AI is a very broad term. Like
there's machine learning, there's that.
But like generative AI has a few things
and that's my opinion. Like it has a few
things that are interesting. I think one
of them is summarization. It can really
summarize. So, like meetings can get
summarized, for example, or any document
can get summarized. It can do an
outline-based creation. So, like you can
give an outline and and some of these
things are already sort of available in
Microsoft 365 now. So, outline to
document is something. And it's also a
change in habit that has to happen. So,
like I think the features and the
capabilities are there. Like people also
need to now start to learn how to use
them. There's a big emerging prompt
engineering field out there. One more
thing which I find is very interesting
is RAG, the retrieval-augmented
generation. So, at least in the context
of, say, a document or a note type of
scenario, you can potentially pull a
bunch of information on a smaller device
now from different parts of the web. So,
like in the past, if you were trying to
say author something, you're going to
Wikipedia, you're going to like 10
websites. Now, you can ask Copilot to
bring some of that information to you,
and also reference it, and so on. So, I
think retrieval-augmented generation is
pretty powerful, and people are using
I've seen many startups that are using
it very successfully, and that could be
a pretty big thing. And then, there are
some of the other scenarios like
translation, which has been around for a
while now. So, I think it's very, very
important that in the context of
whatever your app you're building, how
do these new capabilities help? Because
there is a problem map, like how I
talked about jobs to be done, and then
there's a solution map. So, in the past,
we used to have create, read, update,
delete. Like, if you think about it,
most of the apps were kind of like CRUD
apps, and then databases came, Kafka,
like big data came, and so capabilities
increased, you know, you could process a
lot of data. And now, it's AI, so I
think it's an increase in solution map,
but ultimately, it's on the developers
on how they make it useful for the jobs
to be done. Like, you can throw in a
bunch of AI, like most apps just go and
integrate with OpenAI's API, but like,
there has to be some meaning. It's
almost like saying that
oh, I have an app, and there's this new
database, like 10 years back, 20 years
back, they were apps that would just do
some kind of a read operation or a write
operation on database, because databases
were cool at the time.
Right.
And so, similarly, AI is cool at this
time, but ultimately, the companies that
win will have to find a very meaningful
use case that uses these. There will be
some companies that will not find a use
case, because for some companies,
summarization or or RAG is not relevant,
and and that's okay. It's not the end of
the world. I think there's a lot of
hubris, right? Like, if I don't do
anything with AI, my investor will not
fund me, my career will go nowhere. So,
I think that's a very scared approach.
Yeah.
The problem map and solution have to
align.
One of the things we talked about a few
weeks ago was I just love the way you
framed it. And this is the way I think a
lot of people could think about how to
bring AI into an app is that whatever
somebody might want to go to their
computer to do, how can AI help do that
in an app? Like how can we bring more
desktop class experience? A great
example I've seen in the market is Photo
Room. They
do background removal. It's like
historically that was like you got to go
into Photoshop. You're not going to do
that on your phone. You're going to do
that on a desktop with a big monitor and
you're going to have the tool and you're
going to like do the outline. It was
like a ton of work. And Photo Room came
along and just makes it like seconds
inside an app. And so I like that
framework of thinking of like how do we
bring these desktop class productivity
into mobile on the small screen by using
these new tools and these new
capabilities. And again, like you said,
it's not just about ChatGPT style large
language models. It's also about using
other algorithms and other technologies
that are springing up around the kind of
ChatGPT. So what are some other examples
at Microsoft of kind of bringing those
desktop class experiences into mobile
that have, you know, shown to be really
useful to customers?
I mean, so far what I talked about like
summarization, like meeting
summarization, RAG like retrieval
augmented generation, those are
interesting scenarios and I mean, in
consumer there are a lot of things that
people are trying and some with more
success, some with less success. Some
funny example is like you can now create
a song for your loved one and it will be
like in any language. You can go to Bing
and just tell it to create a song for
you and it's a bit gimmicky, but it's a
real thing. I I'm sure some developers
will probably find a use case for
something like that algorithm because
that algorithm can do things. I don't
think that right now any real songs are
getting created by AI, but that day will
happen. So, I think that that's a more
consumery thing. On the more businessy
side, I think yeah, meeting
transcriptions, recapping meetings,
those are some very interesting
scenarios. Like, you enter a meeting a
little bit late, you can get a recap of
what has happened, your meeting notes
are sent to you, task items are sent to
you. So, I think those are like good
examples of things that are actually
useful because now you don't need that.
And I think one more which is very
interesting which I tried is writing
status updates. So, essentially, I do my
work in Word files, Excel files, etc.
And then Copilot can actually pull a lot
of that information and write a status
on a given topic. So, if I can prompt it
properly, it will write a whole status
that I can then send out to the team. Or
at least write 80% of it, which is
pretty good. Like, it's a big
time-saver. I think it just becomes
super useful when it gets connected with
all the apps that you are working on,
and then it can pull data from your
context because that's live data that
it's pulling. And then it can really
help you write content. A lot of people
are writing books these days with AI. I
think you may have seen like author plus
AI.
Those specific examples aren't going to
apply to a lot of apps, but I think the
thinking behind it is how you have to
think about it. And a couple other
examples you had shared with me were
slide generation in PowerPoint. Like,
being able to on your phone create a
more sophisticated presentation quickly
using AI. And then getting insights from
Excel. Like, if you're on a desktop
computer, what are you going to do?
You're going to sit there with your
keyboard and mouse and create complex
equations, and you're going to reference
web to figure out, you know, how do I do
this exact equation in Excel? And now in
Excel, there's capabilities to use AI to
get some insights from that data. And
so, the way to think about it is that
like jobs to be done. It's like, what
are the things that people would do on
desktop that they can do in the app? And
I thought those were some really good
examples. The other thing I wanted to
talk about is your approach to growth
and the way you think about it. And
again, I was like surprised when we
started talking that your team just in
the past few months implemented an MMP
for the first time. And so you think,
you know, Microsoft's got everything
together and like the biggest company on
there, they've got all the resources,
they're super sophisticated, but like
you're on the learning curve like a lot
of the people here in the audience and
who are going to be listening on the
podcast of like, "Okay, we need to find
new channels to explore." So, how do you
think about growth and, you know,
starting to really push as you have seen
more and more success in selling these
solutions to consumers on the App Store.
How do you approach that growth?
I think one of the things which is and
I'll specifically keep it to sort of
mobile and Mac and App Stores for this
talk, but I mean, we see the App Stores
as the channel which can bring us a lot
of organic traffic. And it can enable
frictionless in-app purchase, for
example, right? And growth that we are
doing pretty much what all of the other
people are doing. And you're right, like
we're not as advanced as one would
think. Like, so we have a pretty good
ASO story in general. We have user
research that kind of informs us what
kind of scenarios are important. We also
get a lot of like Gen Z trend and those
kind of things. And then we're able to
take that and put it in our keyword
optimization. And then we also have a
jobs-to-be-done approach. Like we know,
okay, we think that, okay, these are the
10 things that we really want our apps
to rank for. And because it's a very
broad app, we have over time also become
good at, okay, what are the things that
people are willing to pay for. So, I
think it's important to know that and
I'm just going a little bit deeper into
keywords. Like, what kind of customers
do you want to acquire? The ones that
will actually
find value enough that they will want to
pay for the premium subscription. So, we
are getting better there and then we are
integrating with an MMP. I mean, I think
one of the things that happened in the
2015 to 2018 era, we got MMP, we got an
engagement platform, etc.
And we kind of misimplemented some of
that because one of the things I mean,
it wasn't it was a combination of a lot
of things. So, what happened in that
time like privacy laws changed a lot
like GDPR came along, and we are under
more scrutiny than any other app. And we
have enterprise customers, so we sell
one app. It's one app for all customers,
enterprise and consumers. So, I think
the implementations they were not done
in such a way that it could handle GDPR
and handle and and also like a lot of
the software companies, most of them in
this conference like they were also
pretty young back then, and the
solutions weren't very advanced. So, at
that time we had an MMP, we had an
engagement platform, and one of the
things that we kept facing was actually
two things we kept facing. One was
privacy issues because privacy laws were
changing really, really fast.
And the second thing that we also faced
at that time was just like value that we
were getting from these software because
we were paying these big bills because
we had a very big monthly active user
base even at that time. So, we were
paying these big bills, but we were not
really using it because on one side we
were just figuring out the products
because at that time like the products
were not at a place where you could
start doing optimization. So,
optimization comes much after your
product market fit is there. So, we
obviously had product market fit in a
big way on desktop, but it took some
years to kind of get that same
stickiness on mobile where we saw,
"Okay, our mobile apps, our iPad apps
are now like at a point where we can now
start doing optimization." So, I think
now the pendulum is turning again. Now,
we are okay. We are at a point where the
apps have good product market fit, and
now we are optimizing. So, MMP is there,
ASO strategy is there. We try to use all
of Apple's promotional offers, promo
codes, and contingent pricing is a new
thing. We're looking into that. So, we
we try to be
as up-to-date with whatever we can do
with these apps. One of the problems
that we always run into is just
justifying the business case for some of
these things. So, when you have an app
that has double or triple-digit million
MAU, then most of the time the magnitude
of opportunity has to be very high. So,
it's so it's like the team size doesn't
grow the same way how your MAU is
growing, right? Like because also team
size cannot grow. You cannot like
because like to add one engineer or say
to add 10 engineers, you also need a
manager. Your team size doesn't exactly
grow, and all of you know that. So, our
thinking has to keep growing.
As our MAU is growing, we have to think
bigger and bigger, and and our
prioritization has to be more and more
strict because like if you have
double-digit million MAU, you can't be
spending time on an optimization that
will impact 1 million users. You have to
be spending time on something that will
impact say 50 or 100, whatever, right?
It's a big number. So, our framework,
our VP, is very very strict about this,
like estimated impact. Any kind of
vendor we have to bring in or anything
that we have to do, any kind of
optimization, he's like, "Okay, give me
the estimated impact." And then we have
this huge list of ideas that come from
all sorts of places, and then we are
like, "Okay, let's triage." And a lot of
times you'd be surprised that the
biggest ideas are the simplest ones.
Like, "Okay, let's do something on
purchase flow or let's do something on
the first-time experience." Because if
you have an app that big, then sometimes
the simplest things, like performance,
reliability, file open speed, size of
the app, those things matter start to
matter a lot.
Yeah.
Are we able to 100% transaction
completion? Because with that kind of
numbers, you know, you we at one point
we were seeing 5, 6% transaction
failure. So, we first have to fix that.
So, I think that is where it becomes
different from startups. Because
It's not all that different though. And
that's what I was thinking the whole
time we were talking is that I think too
many small apps don't have that
prioritization framework in place. I
hear apps all the time. They're like
$100,000 a month in revenue. You know,
like orders of magnitude smaller than
what you're working on. But then they go
try and like oh, we got to have win-back
campaigns.
Mhm.
It's like well, if you're only at
$100,000 a month and you only have
thousands or tens of thousands of users,
like that's not low-hanging fruit. And
so, from the smallest apps in the App
Store to the biggest apps in the App
Store,
you really should be thinking about
these prioritization frameworks. And you
should every feature that you're working
on, every tool that you're going to
implement, every strategy that you're
going to put in place, you should be
thinking and have a hypothesis. Like
what's the real impact going to be to
our business? And again, if you're like
oh yeah, we got to do win-backs, like
that's a huge thing. Well, okay, if a
thousand people are going to churn from
your app over the next 6 months and you
can hope to win back 5 to 10%, like how
meaningful of an impact your business is
that compared to like so many other
opportunities that you can have much
higher impact in your business. I think
that's actually a great way to think
about it. So, as we wrap up, we're going
to link to your LinkedIn, but anything
else you wanted to share? Like is your
your team hiring or like anything you
wanted to share from your end?
I'm actually not sure. My team might be
hiring.
Yeah, no. I I actually don't have that
information top of my head.
But yeah, I mean, please feel free to
reach out for any questions or discuss
any app growth strategy. I'm pretty
active on LinkedIn, so.
Awesome. And then for those of you here
in the audience, as I said earlier, you
know, the Sub Club podcast, we talked to
folks like Ramit every 2 weeks and we
actually talked everybody from like
indie apps who are scaling up,
mid-market apps who are having the same
struggles. And then of course, I do work
for RevenueCat. In these kind of
conversations, I don't talk a ton about
it, but we're a subscription
monetization platform that helps with
all this kind of stuff, kind of that
base layer of infrastructure that does
push data to WinBacks, you know. And
again, I'm I'm not here on stage saying
"Don't focus on WinBacks if you're
early." But as you grow, that's a really
important thing and like our data at
RevenueCat can really help push that. So
yeah, thank every everybody for joining
and hope you enjoyed a conversation
today and check out the Sub Club podcast
and RevenueCat and everything else we're
working on.
Thanks so much for listening.
If you have a minute, please leave a
review in your favorite podcast player.
You can also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.